You know, it's great if if you,
go to the website of the University
of
Tehran, where I am right now.
It's all the cliches of every university.
They have a picture of a
bunch of happy, grads.
They have the required,
photo of a multiracial classroom,
whichever university
has on their website.
All of these people learning.
But let's talk a little
bit more, about what
the— okay, you mentioned like the Ubers
and Lifts, etc.,
like.
What else were people trying to build?
Like, how, how far did this ecosystem push?
And
then you mentioned,
okay, eventually
a company gets to a
point, it reaches some threshold in which,
like, it
is no longer really, able
to like operate as like a private,
entity that pursues shareholder,
value is its mission.
Like, what happened?
Where is?
What's the second?
After all this excitement, like, where does it go?
Yeah, so, I,
mean, I will, say, a
lot of the, the startups, were kind of familiar.
There, were, sort of like,
versions, of things that,
we would, be familiar,
with in, the West.
So there's the Amazon of Iran called Digikala,
there's the Uber of Iran called Snapp,
there's food delivery apps.
There's all sorts of things.
There's also things that are kind of more,
unique.
But but those the most successful companies,
the ones like kind of right out the gate,
are the ones that are sort of taking,
business models that have been
tried, and true in the rest
of the world,
and localizing them for Iran,
so you know they starts to really grow,
and, this kind of takes everyone by surprise,
including the
government, I think.
You
know, from interviews I've done,
it seemed like the government really,
sort of thought this stuff was
sort of, whatever.
You know, like,
okay, I think they didn't quite realize,
how quickly this,
um, this this field would grow.
And,
you know, our character
that we, kind of follow in the book starts,
his own venture capital fund,
first with domestic funding
and,
then brings in a lot of external,
funding as well from Europe,
and Russian investors.
And
this sort of,
I think, takes a lot of the conservative,
kind of established forces by surprise,
and, what we very quickly see is a backlash.
Hello and
welcome to another,
episode of the Odd Lots Podcast.
I'm Joe Weisenthal,
and I'm Tracy Allaway.
Tracy, it's now July twenty-eighth,
and the Iran War continues to go on.
And it's, sort of extraordinary
the fact that you,
know in
the beginning here was this,
thing that was going to be if,
it persisted sort of cataclysmic,
perhaps for the global economy and,
particularly with related to oil prices.
And yet, on a sort of day-to-day basis,
it's not even,
necessarily the biggest headline,
news that most people are talking about.
People get used to a lot of things, very quickly.
I, mean, it,
still, has the,
potential, to be,
catastrophic, at, some,
point, in time,
but, you're,
absolutely right.
We've gone months now since—
when did this start in March, right?
Yeah, very beginning of March.
Yeah,
months now with a war which technically,
hasn't even been declared a war,
it's an operation.
Is that what they're calling it?
Military operation.
I think it's been a long—
people talk about the Forever War.
I think the last—
it's
been a long, time since America actually,
ever acknowledged
that it
was in a capital,
W war.
Very true.
But it does kind of
beg the question,
about what happens
when all of this is over, right?
Yeah, right.
I mean, hopefully it ends one day.
And
I have to say, so obviously,
we talk about oil a lot, when
we talk in terms of economics.
I have to admit, you know, it's funny.
We've done multiple episodes,
about the Iranian stock market,
which is a fascinating topic,
but
other than the fact that obviously,
Iran produces a lot of oil,
I actually like basically, know
nothing about the Iranian economy.
Like the day to day,
what a typical
middle class— there's
some things I know.
So, there's oil.
There's
Iranian cars,
famously.
Which I would be interested in experiencing,
one day, not necessarily buying, but
experiencing pistachios.
I was going to say,
so like pistachio is like nuts,
I imagine, but like what the sort
of job market is,
what a day to day—
um, you know what,
what, what's out there,
and ah, you know, whatever the Iranian,
equivalent of LinkedIn or Indeed dot,
com is—
like what people do,
what people what people want career-wise.
All of these things,
because there's an Iranian stock market.
Obviously, you know,
presumably there are like startups,
and companies that one day want to list,
but I don't know what any of them do.
I have so many questions.
I guess about like what a quote normal,
Iranian— let's imagine
the war ends,
and also there aren't sanctions.
Right?
What would an Iranian—
well, this is my thing because at various
points in time,
previously you have had these,
bursts of optimism
about the opening,
up of the Iranian economy,
the lifting of sanctions—
it's one other thing I
know—
again, not much—
but one thing I know is
it's a huge, economy,
right?
Don't we?
With our previous stock Iranian stock,
market guest, the size of Turkey, right?
Something like that.
It's a really big economy.
It's a big economy,
and so what happens,
if that starts to open up?
Can it open up?
Are we going to
see what happened,
previously, where it kind of starts to
open
up, and then it shuts down again?
I don't know.
I several months ago like,
there was like some random night,
where I was doing what I like.
Clicking
on random Wikipedia links,
and I was like,
"I wonder what Ahmadinejad's,
economic policy platform was when,
he ran for president for the first time."
I like started clicking on his campaign.
I was like, "I wonder."
And it was like seemed kind
of vague,
and he had some—
I wish I could remember the slogan.
It was really good.
It was something like, "If we
imagine it, we can do it."
It was like—
you know— the most inoffensive sort of like,
domestic policy agenda
slogan,
and I couldn't really find that.
More specifics, but you know you have
elections and several.
What do they run on?
What do they you know?
Where do they stand on taxes?
All these questions about sort of like,
yeah normal normal
quote normal unquote,
economic life in Iran.
Is that your way of saying that you,
want to talk about the political,
economy of Iran?
I want to talk about the political economy,
and the even regular economy of Iran.
Anyway,
I'm very excited to say,
we do in fact have two perfect,
guests on who
teach us much more, about this.
We're going to be speaking with Yeganeh,
Torbati, Iran correspondent for the New
York Times, as well as Bozorgmehr Sharafedin.
He's the head of digital
at Iran, International.
So, uh.
Both of you, thank you so
much for coming on Odd Lots.
Thank you so much for having me.
Thanks for having us.
Oh, and, I, should,
of course, mention,
that they,
are the, co-authors, of, a, brand, new book,
*Stolen, Revolution: Betrayal, and,
Hope,
in Modern, Iran*,
so, again, thank,
you, both, so much, for, coming out.
What did we just start?
What is the what is the premise of this book?
Why was this an important book to write,
or what what what what endeavor
did you to go on this project?
Yeah, well, thank you so much for having us.
I mean, we started on
this project around five,
and a half years ago, so late 2020,
and I think our vision
was at first,
we were very focused
on kind of trying to.
As you sort of mention Iran's,
political economy and in particular,
sort of the roots of corruption,
and sort of state control and influence,
over the economy over the past forty,
you know, fifty years,
and then of course,
as time went on,
and since 2020,
a lot of things have happened
in Iran,
and our focus,
both broadened and I think deepened.
But sort of throughout that book is,
throughout, our book is sort of this continuous,
thread of the
promises that the current,
government, the Islamic government,
came to power on in 1979,
particularly around social justice,
and how it might redistribute Iran's,
really immense resources,
and sort of what that has actually,
led to in practice today,
which is far from those promises.
Yeah,
so you describe the Islamic,
Republic as evolving into this,
sort of mafia state,
and I guess there's a difference,
between an authoritarian government,
and a corrupt one—
although they often go hand in hand.
How did how did Iran,
kind of evolve from the authoritarian,
Islamic Republic to a place
that, in terms of its economy, was actually,
extracting value from its people?
Yeah, I think maybe it's good to define,
what do we mean by a mafia state,
and what's the difference,
between a mafia state and a normal,
totalitarian government.
I think in a normal society,
all citizens are equal,
and they, benefit the same from the
government,
and the wealth of a nation.
But in a mafia state,
you should imagine a layered society.
And citizens are rewarded,
based on their loyalty
to the system.
So the more loyal, you are
to the government and the state,
the more, you will benefit from
the resources,
so that's how the Islamic,
Republic was from the
beginning,
and it excluded the its critics.
And it rewarded people who were loyal,
and it was an
ideological government.
So, people,
who, believed,
in the,
values of, the Islamic,
Republic, were rewarded.
But as we move forward,
we see that this trend,
uh, was, uh,
reflected more and more in the economy.
You see that how Revolutionary gods
and other religious foundations—
they come and take,
over the big chunks of the
big
chunks of the economy,
and I can say that this mafia state,
and the layered
society is is even,
reflected in Iran's foreign policy.
So, in the eyes of Iranian states,
maybe a Hezbollah member in Lebanon,
or a
Houthi militia in Yemen—
they are more loyal to the Islamic,
Republic than let's say a critic,
a professor at Tehran University,
so they should benefit,
more from the wealth of the nation.
So that's why we have had
all these, discussions
within the Islamic, Republic that while
the
Iranian, government can't afford
to provide, free milk at schools,
it has the money to give to its,
proxies in the region.
To kind of reward
their loyalty, right?
Maybe I should back up even,
further at this point and ask,
the the Iranian Revolution,
how much of that was about economic,
grievances on the part of the people,
the idea that as so many revolutions are,
you know, things need to get better versus,
just the the clergy basically seizing power?
I think it was sort of a mix
of a few, different things.
You know, the working classes and sort of
the lower, socioeconomic classes did
not really, jump in to be part of the
revolutionary,
coalition until quite late in the game.
Um, you know,
when um, they were they really,
started to suffer from
some of the um,
the Shah's,
economic policies kind of towards the very,
end,
um, really at the beginning it was more,
kind of like the middle classes,
and the intellectuals.
Who were sort of forming,
this kind of revolutionary, coalition
from a bunch of different, impulses?
There were some who wanted,
kind
of an Islamic government,
there were others who
were communists,
and were kind of more anti-US,
anti-imperialist.
And there were others who just wanted,
kind of a secular liberal democracy and,
felt that the Shah was
trampling on people's, rights.
All of those people kind of joined in,
but what we see,
especially, kind of towards
the end of the revolution, as we're getting to
nineteen seventy nine, is that um,
the leader of the revolution,
Ruhollah Hamani, um,
who kind of then, became the
leader of the new government,
he, wanted to kind of co-opt some of the most,
effective sort of leftist arguments,
because, he wanted kind of their
young people,
their supporters,
to sort of also support him.
And so, you know,
these arguments of
kind of the bourgeoisie,
versus the proletariat—
you know, Khomeini kind of
adopted some of those,
terms with an Islamic
tinge— and therefore,
sort of— you know, he promised,
and then in the first few months,
especially of the Revolution, he
also promised that,
you know, we are going to provide for the poor.
We're going to provide free electricity,
free buses for the poor.
We're going to build housing.
And I think you know the government,
sort of wanted to present,
itself as being on behalf of some of
those, the kind of the lower classes of society,
and presented them kind of as its base.
As time goes on,
what we see,
especially kind
of in the last,
ten to fifteen years,
it sort of turned its,
back on a lot of those promises
to where,
it's not even really even pretending,
anymore that that is
kind
of what, it's aimed at, and we can kind of talk
about,
sort of some of the turning points there,
but it really was kind of a gradual,
shift over time,
and, then in the especially since Twenty
seventeen, you really see,
um, this growing um dissatisfaction,
amongst um not just middle class Iranians,
but also people who are poor,
and struggling against what this,
revolution has has brought to them.
So you talk about,
okay everyone's ability
to derive,
wealth or income or is somehow,
linked to where they stand in this,
hierarchy of supporting
the government, or supporting the state.
In some way or another,
let's talk about where the government gets,
its resources to make
these allocations—
whether it's housing,
whether it's electricity,
whether it's obviously,
Um, munitions for various various groups,
etc. Obviously,
we
know oil is a big part of it,
but what are the main?
How would you big,
picture decompose what the Iranian,
economy sort of basically looks like?
So I think of course,
yeah, oil is a big one.
It has kind of
this, this huge resource that's very valuable,
and that it can kind
of use to fund, itself.
But also, Iran has a pretty diversified,
economy in terms of its industrial base.
So, and, that, that is partially, in
as a result of kind, of the Shah's,
own policies, but,
then
also sort of,
this idea, that took,
root after the, Revolution, that,
we need,
to provide, for,
ourselves, we, need, to,
be self-sufficient.
This, was, a, very,
important,
kind, of, part,
of, both, the,
ideology, of,
kind of present, in,
that, moment, in,
general, the,
sort, of, like,
20th century 60s,
70s kind, of, backlash, against,
interference,
by, world, powers,
in, the, internal,
affairs, of,
Iran, and, of,
other, countries.
So there was kind of this very strong,
idea, especially among Iranian leftists and,
including in some of the clerical class,
that we need to kind of establish, our own
industries and be independent.
So Iran has a car industry.
Iran has steel plants that were built,
after the Iran Iraq
war and became,
operational sort of after the
Iran Iraq war,
that produce,
you know, huge amounts of steel,
you know, kind of leading the Middle,
East in in in that industry,
and these, industries are maybe not
necessarily the most, efficient.
Um, and they don't have a ton of foreign,
investment,
but um, they provide employment.
Iran has a huge agricultural sector,
that is, you know,
which
is which is an enormous source of jobs in Iran,
has
been very important.
As it's been under sanction,
of course, the agricultural,
sector has a lot of other costs,
including overuse of water,
which Iran has been facing,
but it was sort—
it's an important, at
least source of jobs in the economy.
So, these, are, all, these, major,
industries, that,
kind, of, first,
start, out, after,
the revolution, being, very,
much, under,
the, purview,
of the, formal, state—, kind, of, what, we,
in, the, West, would, recognize,
as, a, government,
including, you know,
um, and a,
ministry, you, know, a,
ministry, that,
is, answerable, to, Parliament, that, oversees,
for, instance, the,
steel, industry,
or, the, mines, in, Iran.
Over, time, and,
we, can, we, should, kind,
of, talk, about,
this, more, the,
control,
over, those,
industries, moves,
away, from, sort, of,
the, recognized,
parts, of, the,
state, into, kind, of,
this,
shadow, state,
which, is, sort, of, much,
more, linked, to, the,
security, forces, and,
to, these, entities, that,
are,
kind, of, controlled, by,
the, clerics, but, aren't,
really, accountable,
to, the, rest, of, the, government.
Um, but sir,
did you want to add anything there?
Yeah, if if I add a
bit to that,
like because, if you look at
the history of the Islamic,
Republic well,
of course the revolution
started with this,
massive wave of nationalization.
The state took control of the major,
industries—shipping,
mining, banking,
and many more,
but gradually as we come,
forward after decade or two,
the Iranian state,
decided the privatization of
Of these,
major industries,
but I think the main, problem was the
corruption.
But We didn't see real privatization.
So usually, people who were close to
centers of power,
they came and took over
these industries,
and, they like they took them
over with a very low price.
Like imagine,
factories that were owned by the government,
they were taken over by elements,
very close to the security forces,
and so after that,
many of these factories,
they didn't come back to production.
The machinery was sold,
and the land
was turned into maybe a
residential place
to build apartments in,
so we saw that at that level,
but still, as
Yeganeh mentioned,
we have a private sector in Iran.
You know the problem with private,
sector is that if
a business, becomes successful,
and it passes a certain threshold,
you will see the security forces coming,
and knocking on your door,
and they want is their share.
And that's that's again, it's
like a mafia state,
as you can imagine,
if you you have a restaurant in,
I don't know, in in in
mafia movies,
if you have a successful restaurant, they would
come and they,
want their share from these businesses.
And as we showed in the book,
one of the major,
new sectors was the startup sector.
Of
course, this sector was started by many,
Iranians who came,
back from abroad to launch this sector,
but they saw that how the security
forces came,
and forced them to give up these firms.
I definitely want to get into the tech,
startup scene that was,
but before we do,
just in terms of the state like becoming,
more intertwined with the private sector,
I learned two new,
words or I guess terms from your book,
and I'm going to mispronounce the first,
one because I've only ever read it.
I've never said it aloud,
but Bonyadz—is that right?
Bon, Bonyad,
Bonyad, okay,
Bonyad, and then invisible ports.
Can you talk a little bit more about those
two things as sort of examples
of how the state becomes intertwined with
the private sector or the general economy?
Okay, so again,
these religious foundations that were
launched at the
beginning of the revolution and they are very
interesting.
So, like one of them
was this massive foundation
that was established to
distribute the wealth from among the poor,
and it seemed quite
a noble cause.
And of course,
we had other foundations to look,
after the families of martyrs of the Iranian,
War and the veterans of the war.
So these massive foundations they were
established by the
order of the founder of the revolution
Ayatollah Khomeini,
and the heads of those foundations they
had massive power.
So we show in the
book, for example,
that how the
head of one of these,
foundations he wanted
to import some,
wheelchairs to into the country to give,
it to the veterans of war.
But at that time,
the Minister of Industries,
he was against the import because he,
believed that the imports of German,
wheelchairs will be will be undermining
the domestic, production.
But, the, head,
of, foundation,
he, was, an, MP,
at, that, time, member,
of, the,
Parliament, so,
he, went, to, the,
Parliament,
and, passed,
a, bill, to,
allow, the, foundation,
to, import, anything,
they, want,
without, any,
government's, supervision.
And, he, wanted,
to, do, that, to, maintain,
the, revolutionary,
nature, of,
the foundation, and, he, didn't,
want, to, be, constrained,
by, bureaucracy,
and, red, tape.
It's interesting that the same person,
decades later,
he becomes the Speaker of the Parliament,
during the reform movement.
And he founds these invisible ports,
or invisible jetties.
That how is that?
So we see that these foundations, and the
Revolutionary gods.
they had massive
power to import,
anything they wanted without audit,
and without taxation,
and this character of the
book—decades later—he goes to southern
ports of Iran,
and he saw a dedicated,
port that belonged to the Revolutionary,
Guards, and they could
import anything they wanted,
without any supervision of the government.
So in a way,
you see how
this mafia state was
formed, gradually.
How, the, revolutionary,
nature, of, the, foundation,
like, force,
them, into, creating,
a, system, which,
was, not, transparent,
from,
the, start, and,
later, on, this,
the, same, system,
turned, into,
a, mafia, state.
And you sort of see how there is some,
good intentions, right?
Like the idea of importing higher,
quality wheelchairs from abroad
to help, veterans of the war who had been
injured.
You know that—that is a laudable intention,
but—he—you know this character, this person
that we're talking about—Mentikow,
to be—he, sort of in that decision
in the nineteen,
eighties,
establishes
this idea that these,
foundations—and it wasn't just
him—but this was
just one example—these foundations are
above the law,
and they get special dispensations,
and special privileges because they're,
kind of associated with the revolutionary, state.
Private companies don't get those rights.
Entities, you, know, that, are,
that, are, disconnected,
from, the, government,
don't, get, those, rights.
But he establishes that and
that same, thinking you know as it continues,
and is not challenged over the years.
Sort of grows into eventually these,
invisible ports and many other abuses.
It's so striking like listening to this,
because you, I mean on the
one hand obviously Iran.
Very distinct story,
but on the other hand,
you know so many of these,
themes we've already discussed—
you see like,
echoes of them or versions
of them in all,
sorts of developing
states or whatever— you know.
Obviously, when you talk about,
oh, here is a steel factory,
some industrial facility,
and then it's been repositioned in some,
way for some non.
Non-vital thing— you sort
of think about late age,
late era Soviet
Union, for example.
It's like, here's the company that wants
to make, bread but
they just
sell all their,
parts abroad for.
Uh, you know hard cash and,
then don't actually serve
their purpose.
Was there ever, was there
ever any, forces
in government
that
tried to keep,
some of these entities in line?
I assume there must be like some,
conflict or effort.
To sort of maintain this thing,
where you have something that resembles,
industry, has some perverse incentives to
maybe,
like take some shortcut for the personal,
gain of whoever is the controlling entity.
Were there ever,
attempts to build in mechanisms,
such that these quote,
public perhaps public resources,
couldn't be expropriated in some way?
For, sure, I, mean, there, were, definitely,
people, who,
um.
Maybe, too, late, sort,
of,
saw, the, errors,
of, some, of, the, the, ways,
that, the, government,
had, acted, including, people,
who, had, been, part,
of the, problem, you, know, in, earlier, on,
in, their, career.
So like.
For example, Mettika Ruby,
who we mentioned,
who was a cleric,
who an MP, he led one of
these one yods,
but, then later on becomes
part of the reform,
movement and rises to great power.
But Oldt and tries,
when he is in parliament to establish,
some standards of transparency for these,
entities, these bonyads,
and other institutions that answer,
directly to
Iran's supreme leader.
Um, and he's unsuccessful.
By that point, which was the late nineties,
early two thousands,
um, these these entities
and the supreme, leader himself
were just far too powerful,
for the elected government to really.
Put a check on.
There's another anecdote that we,
talk about at length in the
book,
which was in 2004,
when Iran was opening a new airport,
and this is.
You know, a big moment for Iran.
It had been planning this airport actually,
since before the revolution,
of course it was delayed,
you know because of that
and, because of the war,
but this was going to be kind of this,
big moment when,
Iran was going to have
an airport to.
Kind of rival Dubai and Istanbul.
On the day that it's being opened,
the Revolutionary Guards drive,
armored land cruisers onto the runway,
and prevent the first plane from landing.
They have to be begged by the transport,
minister before they allow it to land.
When the second plane wants to come in,
they scramble a fighter jet and threaten it,
and it has to divert
south to Esfahan.
And why did this happen?
The the transport minister later revealed
in a series of interviews,
because the guards had wanted the contract
to operate that airport,
but they hadn't provided the best price.
And so the government had given,
it to a Turkish Austrian firm,
and you know the airport was shut down.
It was basically a no fly zone for months,
and it was reopened with state.
Firms running the airport,
rather than this foreign contract.
And so, you know,
our character Matthew Cowby—
he's a Speaker of Parliament,
his Parliament, his MPs—
write a report.
About what happened,
but ultimately there's,
no accountability for for that action,
and as we go on in time,
you know, there's there's.
We get to a point, where the guards don't
even,
really have to take such a dramatic step.
Their dominance in contracting and in,
you know, different parts of
Iran's economy, sort of goes unquestioned,
and I think.
The element of Iran's government that is
somewhat unique,
at least in its specifics,
from you know a place
like the Soviet Union or other places,
is that because
all of these institutions
answer to someone who sort of is seen as a
holy.
Figure and whose power comes from.
God, effectively,
it's much more difficult
to question both his authority
and to
establish any accountability over
institutions that only report to him,
which is how.
Iran's government is structured.
Both the military and these big bonyads,
only report to him.
And how can you question someone who's,
you know, effectively God's representative?
The extraction from the private.
Sector,
how much of that is about consolidating,
political power?
And how much of it is about,
I being worried
about, I guess foreign,
threats that might come in through,
additional capital in the country.
Like, can you kind of
decompose, or try to maybe psychoanalyze
the?
The motivations for,
for instance,
the Iranian guards wanting to stop a new,
airport from operating.
I think the way I see,
it is the
competition of different,
factions within the same system.
Yeah, it's not.
That one faction, wants to have all the money,
and the other faction is promoting,
transparency and is fighting corruption.
Usually, you see.
With a
change of government,
to see that
how the new,
government tries to empower people,
and elements
close close to that,
and we explain that in the book and how.
For example, Ahmadinejad,
when he came to power,
he tried to empower people close to him.
But when next presidents,
when they come,
including
Hassan Rouhani,
we see that.
He also tried to.
Somehow make sure that people,
closer to him have like.
People, close close to him can benefit
from the such, resources.
So I think, there is this in fighting that you,
see that sometimes the Revolutionary,
Guards they need to use their military.
And intelligence power,
and sometimes,
the other faction can take control.
But
overall.
I think there are many,
elements that have added
to this, competition.
Of course, the sanctions are
one of those,
like decades of sanctions.
They have created this,
lack of transparency within within the.
And each faction,
they come and they,
try to take a part of the business,
trying to show that themselves,
essential for the everyday,
affairs of the country to to to be handled.
For example,
Iranian
oil ministry,
what has been in charge of selling
ores—that has been the case for for
decades—but
when the sanctions,
increased in in recent decades,
and the government couldn't pay its,
debt to,
let's say, Iran's police and their
military forces,
it it gave them access to oil.
So a big part of Iranian oil,
export has been done by
the Revolutionary, Guards.
At this stage,
some estimate that half of the Iranian,
oil is sold by the Revolutionary Guards.
So, I think the way I see it is just these,
different factions they are constantly,
fighting with one another,
trying to have a bigger,
share of of the of the economy.
Tracy, I think your question—like there's one,
anecdote that sort of like exactly,
answers it, um.
So I think it's both.
I think they both like they,
came by their suspicion of foreign,
intervention in Iran's economy.
Honestly, I mean if you look at the
twentieth century history of Iran,
it is one of Um,
economic exploitation of the country
by world powers—um, U.S.,
the British,
the Russians, etc.—
um, and also they have used that ideology
in a way that has benefited themselves, so
the one anecdote that kind of
gets at
this is in 2020,
2021 when COVID is hitting,
Iran is one of the worst affected
countries by COVID.
The supreme leader,
decides to bar the import
of many, Western doses of
the COVID vaccine,
and kind of almost simultaneously,
the Iranian government, decides
to launch on a project to
make, its own COVID vaccine,
but what's the entity that's, given that
contract?
It's the conglomerate,
controlled by the supreme
leader Ali, Hamani.
So he's both deciding a policy that,
and I think, you know,
if if we—he's no longer with
us—but if we had given him truth serum,
I think he actually was suspicious
of
the motivations of the U.S.
and the British,
and, you know, making these COVID vaccines—
I think,
you know, that was probably genuine—but
also
with with that decision,
he creates a shortage,
and then his conglomerate
that would profit from a government
contract like this is able to step in and
kind of save the day,
and also make these these vaccine doses.
So you kind of see
in that one example,
both the
ideology and the self-interest,
kind of really melding seamlessly,
in a way that,
you know, it's just,
it's just kind of remarkable to me.
So, so I think Bowser's answer stands,
but I also think that it's,
sort of both
of those those factors that you,
identified acting at once.
Yeah, and Joe, I should just say the one other
thing I
know about Iran's
economy is that it has been the subject of
interest to put it mildly to many
of foreign
governments over time, and of course,
famously BP.
You know this right?
BP has its origins as the Iranian
Anglo Iranian Oil Company.
So, one question I have—just again from a
sort of pure
economic developmentalist question—most
of the things that many of the things
that you describe,
they would call like
import substitution in developing
economies, etc.
It's like okay,
like we don't want to import too much of X,
because then our sort of nascent,
company can't compete,
et
cetera, and in many
cases there could be logic.
Was there—have there ever been a figure in,
you know,
modern
ran in history,
who is sort of like the
sort of the export-oriented, development.
Let's build an
industry that can compete.
Is what we always talk about with the,
you know, the East Asian countries.
Let's build an industry, set
aside oil
that that competes,
and that we
want to thrive,
etc.,
and the export,
market will be the test of whether,
this is a successful company or not.
Has anyone like tried this sort of—you
know—this very popular idea?
I think the closest that comes to my,
mind was Hashemi Rafsanjani,
President Hashemi Rafsanjani,
who was saying that he wants to make,
turn Iran into an Islamic
Japan.
So he was very fascinated by metro,
system in Western societies,
and he wanted to create the same system.
But at the end,
I think he failed to do that.
What do you think they gonna?
Yeah, I mean,
I think, you
know, I don't know that
I would, if anyone should cite me on this,
but I, you know,
when I'm kind of looking at sort of how,
Iranian companies compete.
I mean, given the fact that the way the
way the direction the direction the
economy has gone in is,
favoring these entities,
these companies that are linked to
powerful people in the state.
And that's sort of poisonous to competition.
And so the idea that even within Iran's
domestic economy,
the
most,
the really, the truly most talented,
and meritorious companies are
not the ones that rise to the top,
or the most successful, or
get the most market share.
It's the ones that have the are are smart,
enough or able enough to sell,
enough of their shares to some,
powerful entity.
That at least they are then,
protected from being perhaps raided,
or shut down,
or maybe they get some sort of like,
special dispensation from the government,
and then the idea that those,
companies that are themselves,
maybe not the best are then,
going to compete externally,
with like the Siemens of the world or,
um, GE,
it just seems a bit—even
if we set aside sanctions,
um, you know,
being a huge barrier which they are.
It seems a bit unrealistic
to me that Iran would would succeed
in that kind of market.
Although,
you know, Iranian steel
has—you know—they—they
get—they used to get a lot of of.
foreign foreign revenue,
foreign currency from exporting,
steel to various country.
So they are there is a market for some
Iranian goods
but it's, you
know I don't know that they would kind of
be at the top of any sort of world list.
Can we talk about the tech sector, specifically?
Because again, this was
surprising to learn that at one,
point Iran had a vibrant startup scene.
But on the other hand,
it kind of makes sense,
if you think
about a place where,
because of sanctions,
you don't have a lot of Amazons or,
Ubers around.
Then maybe that's the perfect—
ah, you know.
I also just associate,
Iran
with having a lot of young, bright, young
educated young educated people—
yeah, absolutely.
All right.
So,
what did Iran's tech startup scene,
actually look like?
Yeah, I mean, this is a
fascinating chapter,
and one that we really dug into.
So, um, Iran was the second country in the
Middle,
East after Israel to get,
access to the Internet, so it's
a very
kind of like tech-forward,
um, you know,
pioneering country in that way.
um,
And,
You know, towards the end,
sort of the early twenty tens,
more and more,
young people are starting to get online.
The Rohani government,
kind of this more moderate government,
coming in,
they um.
enabled access to three G and four G internet,
and so there was all this—
there is suddenly,
this access to mobile data,
and so the ability to kind of
have apps,
and stream video—
all that, all those sort of things.
So it really took off,
and Iranian users wanted content,
they wanted apps.
And as you mentioned,
sanctions, meant that even
with the nuclear deal,
because the nuclear deal, if
you remember,
did not allow,
American companies to go into Iran.
So the leading tech,
companies in the world—
Amazon, Uber,
Lyft—
they could not operate,
so there's this
sort of protected,
ecosystem of 80 million
at
that time, 85 million or,
so population that needed apps.
And Iranian
businesses could suddenly, um, you know,
launch and and serve those people, and so
that's really what happened.
So
you you kind of start to see the first,
inklings of this sort of tech industry,
forming in the Um,
early twenty tens.
You get some very early foreign investment,
even before the nuclear deal happening,
and um, you know some some Iranian expats
moving back,
and sort of seeing what's happening,
and starting venture capital funds.
And this really then takes off,
after the nuclear deal is signed in 2015,
and goes into effect in early 2016.
And you know foreign investors are just,
really intrigued by this
idea that we,
finally have like the last,
sort of green field opportunity is in Iran,
and
maybe it could be the next Russia,
maybe it could be the next China,
and we could really get in early on this.
and So that you know we kind
of trace what, happens after that.
You know, it's great.
If if you, go to
the website of the University of Tehran,
where I am right now,
it's all the cliches of every university.
They have a picture of a bunch of happy grads.
They have the required,
photo of a multiracial classroom,
whichever university
has on their website.
All of these people learning,
but let's talk a little bit more,
about what the—
okay, you mentioned like
the Ubers and Lyfts, etc.
like.
What else were people trying to build?
Like how how far did this ecosystem push?
And then you mentioned,
okay,
eventually a company gets to a point,
it reaches some, threshold in which like.
it is no longer, really able
to like operate as like a private,
entity that pursues shareholder,
value is its mission.
Like, What happened?
Where is, what's the second?
After all this excitement, like,
where does it go?
Yeah, so I mean,
I will say a lot of the
the startups were kind of familiar.
There were sort of like versions of things
that we would be familiar with in the West.
So there's the Amazon of Iran called Digikala,
there's the Uber of Iran called Snapp,
there's food delivery apps,
there's all sorts of things.
There's also things that are kind of more,
unique.
But but those the most successful companies,
the ones like kind of right out the gate,
are the ones
that are sort of taking,
business models that have been
tried, and true in the rest of the world,
and localizing them for Iran.
So you know they starts to really grow,
and this kind of takes everyone by surprise,
including the government.
I think, you know, from interviews I've done,
it seemed like the government really,
sort of thought this stuff was
sort of, whatever.
You know, like,
okay,
I
think they didn't quite realize,
how quickly this um,
this this field would grow.
And
you know,
our character that we,
kind of follow in the book starts,
his own venture capital fund,
first with domestic funding and,
then brings in a lot of external,
funding as well from Europe,
and Russian investors.
And this sort of,
I think, takes a lot of the conservative,
kind of established forces by surprise,
and, what we very quickly see is a backlash.
And first it,
kind of takes the form of sort of hidden,
kind of whispers.
There's
like a mysterious Telegram,
channel that forms that starts making,
accusations against some of the startup,
founders and and you know sort of people
around that sector.
The startups are very,
much associated in some cases,
they
did
not mean to be, but in some,
cases they did sort of form an alliance.
They are associated with the elected,
government of Hassan Rouhani.
And you know there were already these,
factions kind of developing that were very,
against Rohani, particularly
in the Revolutionary Guards,
and sort of saw him,
and his diplomats as being too,
conciliatory towards the U.S.
So this backlash from the security, state is kind
of forming.
People are being interrogated, they're being—
you know—
sometimes arrested,
even their offices are being raided.
And at the same time,
what we document is that people,
kind of middlemen with a foot in the
security state and a foot in the private sector—
people who had been,
you know, Ministry of Defense officials or
who had served on the boards of some of
these Bonyads, etc.
They start to make an offer to some of the
startups, and basically the offer is,
'Give us like
five percent of your shares,
and we will help protect you
from these accusations and from
the risks that you're facing.'
Um, and some of the the startup
founders, take that deal.
You
know, we really try to get into their mindset,
and we interviewed over seventy,
people for this section of the book,
and I think they they some of them didn't,
understand really what was happening.
They felt beleaguered,
and they felt
quite at risk,
and they wanted to save their companies.
They wanted to do what they felt,
like was good
work—employing people,
providing middle-class jobs—and so some of
them took that deal.
And we see,
um, you know,
ah, for instance,
um, the Uber of Iran, Snapp, sold
a large portion of its,
shares to one of the Bonyads.
There's another um kind of ride-share,
company that launches
with, um, Revolutionary Guard financing.
And then ultimately,
just a couple years ago,
and we sort of trace
the
specifics of this,
and how much the company tried to resist,
but ultimately the Amazon of Iran,
Digikala, um,
did sell 40 percent of its,
shares to a telecom that is part,
owned by one of these Bonyads as well.
So, we really kind of see this this
exciting, vibrant,
thriving industry that was not deeply,
connected to the government over time,
then kind of is subdued
by those, government forces.
By
the way, Tracy,
I
just found this very interesting,
article
from twenty twenty that company
Snap, in order to get onto the—
there's a story from Rest of World—they
got on the Apple App,
Store by disguising
the app as a music,
streaming app, and then
only
upon a user,
logging in with an
Iranian IP address, what its full,
capabilities as a ride-hailing app emerge.
And then, I guess Apple has since banned that,
but some clever ingenuity there.
Yeah,
very smart.
Okay.
So one thing I'm wondering is,
at the time of this tech
boom, such as it was,
there were some Iranian,
officials that seemed
to be supportive of it.
I can't remember his exact name,
but there was someone in the ministry who
was like
actually actively promoting tech,
at the same time that you
had other actors in the
government who are starting like
disinformation campaigns
to smear these companies and making you
know not so subtle threats
and things like that.
Again,
I'm fascinated by fascinated by the
coordination,
problem or lack of coordination here,
because it really seems like,
people are like off doing different,
things, and if you're a business owner,
how are you supposed to respond
to all these competing interests?
Um, I, I I can add a little bit of this.
I think, um,
that that is the the huge challenge that like,
you know, Iran is not just,
for instance, a corrupt,
state or just an authoritarian state.
It's also sort of chaotic,
and I, think that is what is
poisonous to business,
almost more than any other
part of it, you know.
I'm not a China expert,
but
my sense is that
you know, when it comes to
China, if, you have an understanding with
the Communist,
Party, then you're good to go.
In Iran,
even if you do end up making a deal with,
you know,
some Bonyad selling your shares,
whatever it might be,
there's, it's,
it's a mafia structure,
but there's also all these underbosses and,
they all kind of compete with each other,
and their power sways from day to day.
So yes,
one entity within the government was really,
supporting these startups,
and wanted them to succeed,
and his,
administration was sort of hated by the more,
powerful security forces.
So, for the startup guys,
a lot of whom were coming— you know—
they were expats—
they were kind of coming back to Iran.
They were bewildered by this,
and as you both know, I
mean business requires
certainty,
and that has been,
I think, more detrimental the uncertainty,
and around the instability
of the actual,
government structure and figuring,
out what it wants from day to day,
that's been more poisonous,
almost than the actual fact of like,
okay I got it make a deal with like such,
and such entity and,
you know, be able to continue my my work
safely.
You know,
the the closest comparison that comes to my,
mind
is
like Greek mythology.
I'm reading Odysseus.
And I see, I,
I am reading Odysseus,
and I realize that Zeus,
doesn't have the absolute power.
So, Iran's supreme leader, didn't
have the absolute power.
He
he needs to manage
between all, difference.
gods and goddesses,
and in the in the case of Odysseus,
you see that he
is supported by some,
gods to go back home,
but some angry gods are trying to block,
his return to back home.
So, yeah, I think a businessman in Iran should,
should, it is just like it is a real Odyssey.
I love this analogy because it's like,
what what what was the breakthrough of
monotheism.
Was
it part to solve this, problem
of different people petitioning,
different gods, etc.?
So you want to like establish no,
there is like one set of rules.
So I think that um,
that's apt,
but also that sort of actually,
brings me to another
question which came,
up a little bit earlier.
But you know when we when we talk about,
some of these things,
we can draw these analogies.
Oh, there may be comparisons
to late Soviet Union.
There may be comparisons to the oligarchs,
extracting the resources,
after the collapse of the Soviet Union.
There may be analogies
to a country, like Venezuela,
which of course people have also,
likened to a mafia state.
There are analogies to China,
with the difference between the CCP,
and the government itself.
The thing that feels a little distinct,
here is the role of religion,
which you meant,
and the idea that there is maybe,
this other
higher thing that um,
people are told to strive towards.
Can you talk a little,
bit more about like teasing,
out the effect that that sort of like,
spiritual element plays
in some of this,
which I could imagine a — creates
yet another difficult,
dimension for businesses to operate in,
but then also when I, especially,
when I think of
the tech sector,
like tech fries people's brains,
and if I, wanted to have a more spiritual
society,
I don't know how much I,
want the public to
be looking at their, phones
all day.
Yeah, I think that's a good point,
because I think that's been one of the
core problems when Western societies have
been trying to tackle
the Islamic Republic of Iran.
Look, Obama tried to have a nuclear deal
with Iran,
and Trump is trying to do that.
I think one of the reasons that the U.S.
and many Western,
countries try to do that was their deep,
belief in market,
free market economy,
and capitalism.
I think the underlying,
assumption was that,
given Did a choice between isolation,
and sanctions and prosperity,
of course, every country
will choose the latter.
Like
in a way, they,
believe that the
by integrating the Iranian,
economy into the into the world,
they will create,
some political liberalisation,
and some form of democratization.
But I think,
I mean,
Trump also believes that if you look at
Trump's speeches in 2025,
he says, "Oh,
I want to make Iran a great nation.
We want I see a bright future for for the
country but."
You see surprisingly that Iran doesn't,
take that offer.
The Islamic Republic I think that's,
when that this ideological component
comes in.
That is somehow difficult
to explain in,
for the Western societies,
that you see that the the country is much,
focused on the ideological aspects of it.
And even after the nuclear,
deal that Obama managed to sign
in 2015, and the lifting of sanctions in
2016,
the money that came to Iran,
the incentives that the Western,
Society has offered,
it was spent on
military development.
So the Iranian state has different,
priorities when it comes to development.
They prefer to put the money on military,
development rather than
on tackling, unemployment,
inflation, and things like that.
So that's been a challenge,
and I think a challenge,
exists at the moment as well.
Like now,
the deal, the Memorandum of Understanding,
that was signed between Trump,
and the Islamic Republic
of Iran —
they offered billions of dollars,
even hundreds of billions of dollars,
but it seems that some elements —
some hard-line elements —
within the Islamic Republic,
they didn't want that.
Tracy, I think from the perspective of the West,
most people, if they're being honest,
cannot believe that some,
people aren't just motivated by money.
Like they hear like.
people say, "Oh,
we believe in some higher power or,
some vision,"
but I think,
like, deep down,
we all believe that everyone has a
price,
and that everyone actually,
just wants like no,
what they really they're saying this,
but what they really want is wealth.
And so I do think like there is this
disconnect when we encounter,
when we have
relationships with people who actually
may believe in something
that is not just accumulating wealth
and comfort — some
people in the West.
I think most people in the West.
Well, okay, but on this note,
what is Iran's political economy?
You know,
the the story we just heard about chaos
and competing factions and all of
that suggest for the future of the
Iran-U.S. conflict.
We see this right now.
Right, there is multiple factions inside Iran.
There is kind of this hard-line,
faction that is really harshly,
attacking the president,
and the foreign minister for even, having
the temerity to sort of negotiate, this
memorandum of understanding.
There are people who kind of still,
want inside Iran for this For to continue,
because they really believe that
Iran, kind of had the U S on the back on
the back foot in
terms of like,
how Iran's political economy
looks, going forward.
I think it's still quite early to say,
um, at this point,
just because they're
still,
sort of in the midst of this war,
really, and I think no one in Iran,
right now is looking that far ahead.
To the extent that they are,
it's very much towards China as the future.
The um Mohammed,
Bawagalybof the Speaker of Parliament,
the guy, who's been kind
of negotiating
with with JD,
Vance,
um, he
he he basically said that as well.
He said that, you know,
we want kind of a a
we want investment,
but they want it from China.
I
don't know if you, want
to add anything on that or, if anything came to
mind.
Yeah, I agree.
I think one thing that I,
want to add is that again,
the different nature of these states,
like — look —
Trump is fighting
at best for
his legacy, but the Islamic,
Republic is fighting for its survival.
I think that creates different pain,
tolerance and pain thresholds in among,
these two nations.
For the U.S.
administration,
the main problem is now,
if the Fed would increase the interest,
rate by zero point
twenty five percent,
and the impact of that on on mortgage rates,
and and other things,
and of course,
people are unhappy with the rise of gasoline,
prices by a dollar or so.
But when you look at the Islamic Republic,
you see that That.
the inflation is almost,
three figures,
and they're not that much,
affected by that.
The unemployment rate
is very high,
and even when you,
come to when you compare the casualties
for the U.S.
administration,
the death of eighteen soldiers
is a lot, is significant.
While for the Islamic
Republic, the killing,
of the death of hundreds or thousands of
soldiers is something that can easily absorb.
So, I think,
that that,
is the nature,
of the the conflict,
that, at this,
stage, and, I think,
the reason,
is that, the Islamic,
Republic,
has survived,
the war, so,
far, is, that,
its pain, threshold is much higher.
And
I think if it continues like that,
I think the U.S. administration
— I don't think they will continue the
war,
because of the long-term impacts,
it will have on the economy.
Of course,
Trump is trying to keep the the price of
oil, under one hundred dollar.
per barrel.
Any time that it touches 100,
there is some talks for
negotiations,
and some positive through social
posts, but I think,
they can manage to do that
for a bit, but I don't,
think it can continue for for a long time.
I think the pattern that we saw,
kind of throughout reporting
this book, and that we really see now
is that, for the Islamic Republic of Iran,
the economy has
never been an end,
goal in and of itself.
It's, focused,
on it,
to the, extent, that,
it's a, means,
to a, broader,
end, goal of,
self-sufficiency,
or, some, kind of, like, drawing,
some, sort, of ideological, strength,
from it, but,
in terms of, actually,
focusing, on the, economy,
at the, expense of,
for, instance, some,
of its, ideological,
goals, that,
has never been, in its, pattern of behavior.
And there are former officials like— don't you
have to take it from us?—
there are former officials who have said,
'You know, it's time to set aside our ideology,
and our foreign policy',
and focus on the economy, which would mean
bringing in foreign,
investment,
which would mean coming to some final,
accord with the U.S. that would really
lift sanctions,
so that we can actually,
move on and grow the economy.
And the whoever's been in power at any
point—
mostly the supreme leader— for thirty-seven
years—
but before that,
Khomeini, of course—
has not taken that bet for them.
The important thing has always been Iran's,
ideology, and I think,
you know, unless there's some drastic change,
I don't necessarily expect that to change.
I would need to see a lot more,
evidence of that actually
You know,
shifting before,
I would kind of change my assessment
on that.
All right, Yeganeh and
Bozorgmehr, thank you both,
so much for coming on the podcast.
Absolutely fascinating discussion.
Yeah, really appreciate you taking your time.
Thank you, I really enjoyed it.
Thank you both so much.
Tracy, I found that I really, enjoyed that
conversation.
I learned a lot.
I,
really, did,
mean, what I, said, in the,
conversation, which,
is that, I do,
think, a lot,
of, American,
or Western, like,
negotiators, and thinkers,
just, sort, of like,
constitutionally,
find it, hard,
to believe, that,
people, in much of,
the, world, actually,
believe, in, things, and,
aren't, just, like,
going, to, be transactional,
at, the end of the day.
That's why my first question was about,
how much of the
Iranian, Revolution was driven by economic,
interest versus actual ideology.
But yeah, I totally take the point.
Um.
I also thought it was interesting.
You know, when we think about emerging
markets,
there's,
plenty of investment
that goes into emerging,
markets, right?
But it feels like the stability point,
definitely stands out.
You know, you can invest in an authoritarian,
regime
totally, if you know you're bribing the
right, person and you're not going to have all,
your
assets seized in like two weeks,
or something by a competing faction.
But when it comes to Iran, it does
seem that factional element,
that chaos,
as they described it, has been an issue.
Yeah, I thought the point,
about the sort of like—
you know, in China,
you have there's the Chinese government and,
then there's the party, right?
And they're not the same thing,
but they're closely linked.
But the idea that like,
okay, what if you have like a more multiplayer,
element, where it's like,
okay, you have some entities that are like,
truly like— this is the state,
and there are state interests,
and then, you have Revolutionary Guards
interests,
and then you have religious interests,
etc.,
and then you really do get, this sort of like
potential misalignment.
I love the analogy of like,
the sort of like petitioning the various,
Greek gods is
like a way to think,
about a sort of like,
problem of
establishing that stability.
It's almost like—
it's like—
it's like okay, like a gangster,
state might not be the worst,
thing in the world,
if there were just one gang,
right?
But right, if there is just one gang.
No, Yeah, like if there is just one gang.
Now, think about like—
think of like a
mafia story, right?
Part of the— it's like, okay,
I'm going to pay this this mafia.
I don't really need the
protection for my, store—
this come, this guy comes and said,
'I'll protect your,
store'
from damages for some insane,
amount— I don't need
it, but whatever, I'm gonna pay it.
You know, but then the moment there's
three gangs,
and each
of them wants that cut,
then, it becomes like a seriously big problem.
No,
and also they get mad at
you for paying, one of them.
So
like, I prayed at the temple of Zeus,
and because
I sacrificed to go to Zeus,
Poseidon is now upset at me,
and now I have
to appease Poseidon,
and then I'm going to appease Poseidon.
And then I don't know,
Aphrodite or whoever is going to get mad.
It just goes on and on.
Right, if Zeus just demanded—
if your only issue was the sacrifice,
Zeus demanded, you might not like it,
but you could form a business
with those, expectations.
And that would probably be—
you find a way to survive—
but then
you have this multi-level thing,
and you can't form that expectation.
Did I ever tell you about in Tokyo,
a friend of mine had a bar?
Tiny bar, ten seats at the bar,
and he got extorted by the Yakuza.
Really, yeah.
And so what happened
is,
there were only ten seats at the bar.
He noticed, first of all,
he got a request for money for protection,
money from the Yakuza,
and he said, 'No, I'm not going to pay it.
I'm a foreigner.
I don't have to.'
Bla bla bla.
Next night,
a single Japanese man
comes into the bar,
orders one beer,
sits at the bar,
all night taking up that
seat—
not a big deal,
plenty of other people around.
Next night,
two people come in,
two Japanese salary
men sit there,
order one beer,
don't leave the entire night.
You can see where this is going.
Within ten days,
all of his seats were being taken,
up by single customers
ordering, single beers.
Wow, and it didn't happen anymore after that.
So, you know,
I won't say
infer how the problem was avoided
going forward.
Exactly.
That's a good story.
Anyway, I'm really glad—
uh, I'm really glad we did that episode.
I learned quite a bit.
Absolutely.
All right.
Shall we leave it there?
Let's leave it there.
This has been another episode of the Odd, Lots
Podcast.
I'm Tracy Alloway.
You can follow
me at Tracy Alloway.
And I'm Joe Weisenthal.
You can follow me at The Stalwart.
Follow
our producers: Cameron
Rodriguez at
Cameron Erman,
Dasho
Bennett
at
Dashbot, Caleb Brooks at Caleb Brooks,
and Kevin Lizzano at Kevin Lloyd Lizzano.
And for more Odd Lots content,
you should check out our daily newsletter.
You can find that at Bloomberg,
dot com forward slash oddlots.
And you can chat about all of these,
topics twenty four seven in our Discord.
Discord dot gg slash oddlots.
And if you enjoyed this
conversation,
then please leave a comment,
or like the video,
or better yet, subscribe.
Thanks for watching.